Pola Nirenska Collection
Music Division, Library of Congress
Guides to Special Collections in the Music Division of the Library of Congress
Pola Nirenska Collection1910-1992 (bulk 1950-1992)
ML31.N57
Nirenska, Pola
10,408 items 30 containers 38 linear feet
Music Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Correspondence, choreographic notes, music manuscripts, poetry, personal papers, biographical materials, including interviews, articles, reviews, and newspaper clippings, programs, publicity materials, such as flyers and posters, scrapbooks, art work, including costume designs, photographic material, memorabilia, books, and other papers relating chiefly to Nirenska's career as a dancer, choreographer, and educator in the United States. The bulk of the collection consists of photographic material. Choreographic notes include those for The Four Horsemen of the Apocalpyse and art work is from Nirenska's early career in Europe and includes costume designs, drawings, and paintings. Correspondents include Evelyn de la Tour, Martha Graham, Louis Horst, Doris Humphrey, Kurt Jooss, Harald Kreutzberg, Rudolf von Laban, Phyllis Legters, Liz Lerman, Dorothy Gifford Madden, Beth Osgood (Chanock), Nicole Pierson, Naima Prevots, Ronald Reagan, Rona Sande, Walter Sorell, Erika Thimey, Jan Tievsky, Jan Veen, Mary Wigman, and Sharon Wyrrick.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
De la Tour, Evelyn--Correspondence.; Graham, Martha--Correspondence.; Horst, Louis--Correspondence.; Humphrey, Doris, 1895-1958--Correspondence.; Jooss, Kurt, 1901-1979--Correspondence.; Kreutzberg, Harald, 1902- --Correspondence.; Laban, Rudolf von, 1879-1958--Correspondence.; Legters, Phyllis--Correspondence.; Lerman, Liz--Correspondence.; Madden, Dorothy Gifford, 1912-2009--Correspondence.; Nirenska, Pola--Correspondence.; Nirenska, Pola.; Nirenska, Pola.; Osgood, Beth--Correspondence.; Pierson, Nicole--Correspondence.; Prevots, Naima, 1935- --Correspondence.; Reagan, Ronald--Correspondence.; Sande, Rona--Correspondence.; Sorell, Walter, 1905-1997--Correspondence.; Thimey, Erika, 1910-2006--Correspondence.; Tievsky, Jan--Correspondence.; Veen, Jan, 1908-1967--Correspondence.; Wigman, Mary, 1886-1973--Correspondence.; Wyrrick, Sharon--Correspondence.
Subjects
Choreographers--United States--Correspondence.; Choreography--United States.; Dance--United States.; Dancers--United States--Correspondence.
Occupations
Choreographers.; Dancers.; Educators.
Administrative Information
Provenance
Acquisition, Jan Karski (Nirenska's husband), 1993.
Accruals
No further accruals are expected.
Transfers
The audiovisual materials were transferred to the Library of Congress, Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division.
Access and Restrictions
The Pola Nirenska Collection is open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Performing Arts Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Biographical Sketch
Pola Nirenska was born 28 July 1910 in Warsaw. From childhood she was interested in dance despite opposition from her middle-class Jewish family. Nirenska had little early dance training. At age nine, she participated in a summer dance camp for girls. Six years later she choreographed her first work, a dance set to Saint-Saën's Danse macabre, and performed it for her sister in the kitchen of her family's apartment. For recreation, she went to ballroom dances. Nirenska was also interested in gymnastics, singing, drawing, and embroidery. She attended a Catholic school where she was proficient in all art-related subjects and was commended for her scientific drawings. Secretly, she took a ballet class but did not care for it, choosing instead to study modern dance for a few months. At the age of seventeen, Nirenska pressured her parents to let her study elsewhere. She finally persuaded them by locking herself in a room for three days, refusing to eat or sleep, until they slipped a passport under the door. She was permitted to continue her studies on the condition that she promise to content herself with teaching and never dance in public.
In 1928 Nirenska used her dowry to study with Mary Wigman, Elizabeth Wigman, Hanya Holm, and Tina Flade at the Mary Wigman School in Dresden. Nirenska excelled in both dance and music -- particularly percussion. Mary Wigman felt Nirenska was gifted musically and should pursue study in music rather than dance. Much to her father's disappointment, Nirenska refused to shift her focus of study. In three years she graduated with first honors from the Wigman School.
From 1932 to 1933 Nirenska toured the United States and Germany with Mary Wigman's company. When the group returned, Hitler had risen to power and Wigman's school was guarded with Nazi soldiers. As a consequence, Nirenska and all other Jewish students were dismissed. In 1934 Nirenska won first prize for choreography and second prize for solo dance in the International Dance Congress in Vienna. Receiving these prestigious awards allowed her to tour Europe with a program of solos.
A scholarship from the Polish government enabled Nirenska to pursue her studies further. She studied briefly with Rosalia Chladek in Austria but found that Chladek's style did not suit her. During this period Nirenska had an engagement at the Opera in Florence. Mussolini's persecution of the Jews forced her to flee to Poland. In 1935 she moved to London where she married Count John Ledesma, a British film star and Royal Air Force pilot. Nirenska's career flourished as she performed for the Royal Air Force, collaborated with Kurt Jooss and Sigurd Leeder, choreographed Broadway-style shows, founded a studio, worked for the Arts Council of Great Britain, and modeled for fashion designers and artists such as the sculptor Jacob Epstein. Around this time, Nirenska's parents and brother escaped to Palestine while the rest of her family refused to leave their home country; seventy-four family members perished in the war. Nirenska left London in 1949 after she separated from her husband.
Nirenska emigrated to the United States when Ted Shawn invited her to perform at the ninth season of the Jacob's Pillow Dance Festival. In New York she studied with modern dance pioneers Doris Humphrey, Charles Weidman, Jose Limon, Louis Horst, and Gertrude Shurr. Nirenska supported herself by washing dishes in an Italian restaurant and teaching at Adelphia College as well as Dance Arts in Carnegie Hall.
Nirenska made her American debut 16 February 1950 at Boston Conservatory. Dances such as Eastern ballad, A scarecrow remembers, St. Bridget: stained-glass window, Sarabande for the dead queen, La puerta del vino, Peasant lullaby, Mad girl, Dancer's dilemma, and Unwanted child were acclaimed by critics, who referred to her as the "Ruth Draper of the dance." While in Massachusetts, she continued teaching and held a position at the Berkshire Playhouse Drama School in Stockbridge.
In 1951 Nirenska was invited to join Evelyn de la Tour at her modern dance school in Washington, DC. During the same year, Nirenska was guest artist and head of the children's department at the Bar Harbor Summer Dance School. Doris Humphrey is thought to have suggested that Nirenska open her own school and company. In 1956 Nirenska founded the Pola Nirenska Dance Company in Washington, DC; by 1960 she had opened her own studio in a custom built home. The student population of professional and beginning pupils of all ages quickly grew to four hundred. Other teaching engagements included The Washington School of Ballet (academic staff), Madeira School in McLean, Virginia (head of dance department), and Glen Echo Dance Theatre in Maryland (choreographer in residence). With Louis Tupler and Ethel Butler, Nirenska founded the Performing Arts Guild, an association of modern dance companies in the Metropolitan area.
In 1969 Nirenska married Jan Karski, a specialist on communism and a former diplomat active in the Polish underground. Karski sent Nirenski a fan letter after he saw her perform, and six years later they married. In 1967 Nirenska joined her husband on a lecture tour to seventeen countries in Asia and French-speaking Africa, during which she gave workshops and master classes in Istanbul, Izmir, Athens, Thessaloniki, and Beirut. One year later Nirenska retired citing fatigue from teaching and running her studio. While in retirement, she focused on other creative outlets, most notably photography. She won awards in area competitions and became a professional portrait photographer. During her retirement, she also enjoyed volunteer work, gardening, performing arts, and travel.
During the 1980s Nirenska was urged out of retirement by leading dance figures in Washington, DC. Nirenska reworked some of her former dances before choreographing new solos and group pieces for the finest dancers in the area. She taught at The Dance Exchange with Liz Lerman, and was a teacher and resident choreographer at Glen Echo Dance Theater with Jan Tievsky. In 1980 she won the Metropolitan Dance Award. The Washington Performing Arts Society presented a concert devoted to Nirenska's choreography in March 1982 at the Marvin Theater. The event was a collaboration between The Dance Exchange, Glen Echo Dance Theater, and the Contemporary Dancers of Alexandria. Other performances ensued with dancers such as Liz Lerman, Jan Tievsky, Rima Faber, Sue Hannen, Betsy Eagan, Diane Floyd, Colette Yglesias, Sharon Wyrrick, Cathy Paine, Stephanie Simmons, Jan Taylor, and Meryl W. Shapiro. Hannen worked with Nirenska for more than a decade and eventually became her rehearsal director.
In July 1990, a farewell concert of Nirenska's works was presented at Dance Place featuring Rima Faber and Sharon Wyrrick. The entire Holocaust tetralogy was performed: Life (Whatever begins also ends), Dirge, Shout, and The train. The tetralogy is prefaced by a quote from Seneca: "In memory of those I loved... who are no more." Nirenska was fortunate always to be one step ahead of the Nazis, but the loss of loved ones had a profound impact on her life. Rather than graphically depicting events, Nirenska's choreography expresses the suffering of Holocaust victims. The tetralogy exhibits Nirenska's intense and powerful expressionist style at its finest.
Nirenska committed suicide 25 July 1992 in Bethesda, Maryland. She is remembered as a matriarch of dance whose works encompassed German Expressionism, the humanistic tradition of American modern dance in the Humphrey-Weidman vein, and the Holocaust. Her teaching contributions are notable as well: she stressed a serious study of dance history, composition, aesthetics, art history, drawing, music history, drama, and Labanotation. Wigman's influence can be seen in Nirenska's philosophy that every educated dancer should be able to read a musical score and play at least one instrument. In 1982 Nirenska said, "Look around, see people, buildings, everything, so you are able to pull all reactions to them into choreography." Throughout her career Nirenska acted as a clear reflection of the achievements of the pioneers of modern dance, and one can see her use of this philosophy in all her work.
Scope and Content Note
The Pola Nirenska Collection consists primarily of biographical materials, correspondence, choreographic notes, programs, publicity, scrapbooks, photographic materials, art work, and audiovisual materials. Excluding published books and recordings, the collection spans the years 1927 to 1992. The bulk of the documents date from the 1950s to the 1990s -- the period of Nirenska's career in the United States -- but the collection contains many valuable materials from her early career in Europe.
Biographical materials in the collection encompass articles, reviews, publicity clippings, and interviews from many countries, including Poland, Germany, and Russia. The clippings and articles date from 1933 to the end of Nirenska's dance career. Newspaper clippings have been photocopied for preservation purposes. Additional clippings and articles are contained in the scrapbooks and subject files. The interviews span from 1966 to 1986 and are in printed form. Three interviewers are identified: Olga Nuray Olcay, Suzan Moss, and Priaulx Rainier. Two interviews were originally housed in the scrapbooks.
Correspondence in the collection, spanning from 1934 to 1992, consists predominately of letters to Nirenska from students and colleagues. Correspondence from the following renowned dance personalities is included: Martha Graham, Louis Horst, Doris Humphrey, Kurt Jooss, Harald Kreutzberg, Rudolf Laban, Phyllis Legters, Liz Lerman, Dorothy Madden, Beth Osgood Chanock, Nicole Pierson, Naima Prevots, Rona Sande, Walter Sorell, Erika Thimey, Jan Tievsky, Evelyn de la Tour, Jan Veen, Mary Wigman, and Sharon Wyrrick. Other letters are from political figures, such as Ronald Reagan, and international and national organizations. Only a few letters by Nirenska are contained in the collection.
The collection contains notes for a number of works choreographed by Nirenska during her residence in the United States. The choreographic notes are mainly textual descriptions, but some are in Nirenska's own notation system. Notes for The four horsemen of the apocalypse are the most abundant. There are also numerous unidentified choreographic notes. Several of the notes were found on or in audio recording tape boxes.
The programs in the collection consist of printed and typescript programs of performances by Nirenska and performances by others. The programs of performances by Nirenska date from 1933 to 1990. More programs can be found in the scrapbooks and subject files, and additional information may be obtained from the addresses and cards in the personal papers series. Nirenska saved only a few programs of performances by others; these date from 1931 to 1988.
Publicity materials, distinct from publicity articles found in biographical materials, encompass printed and typescript documents such as flyers and posters. Publicity about Nirenska dates from 1933 to 1990. More materials can be found in the scrapbooks and subject files. Publicity about others dates from 1927 and 1992. Nirenska saved only a few publicity items about others.
The scrapbooks comprise particularly informative sections of the collection. Thirteen scrapbooks consisting of photographs, clippings, articles, programs, publicity materials, and correspondence were compiled by Jan Karski. Coverage begins in 1933 with Nirenska's early career and ends with materials concerning her death in 1992. Documents from her sojourns in the United States, Poland, Austria, England, Italy, Israel, Switzerland, Turkey, Greece, and Lebanon are included. Original order of the scrapbooks has been maintained; materials are generally in chronological order.
Photographic materials comprise the bulk of the collection, spanning the 1930s to 1992. The series is divided into three subseries: photoprints, negatives, and slides by Nirenska. Photoprints are divided further into prints of Nirenska alone; those of other people; those by Nirenska; those by David Hasamatsu; and those housed in albums. Prints are black-and-white and are 8 x 10 inches or less in size unless noted otherwise. Works choreographed for dance solo are found in "Nirenska alone;" group works with Nirenska as a performer are located in "Nirenska with others;" and group works not including Nirenska are found in "Other people."
The prints of Nirenska alone are made up of both publicity and informal shots. Included are early solo works such as Eastern ballad, Felina -- catty woman, A scarecrow remembers, and Unwanted child. There are also prints of Nirenska as a model in England. Other publicity and informal shots are contained in the sub-subseries of Nirenska with others. Of particular interest are photographs with Mary Wigman and of works such as Departures, American folk suite, and Shakespearean suite. Prints of others are publicity and informal portraits and late works by Nirenska without her as a performer. In addition to portraits of dance personalities, there are photographs of the artist Felix Topolski. The sub-subseries of prints by Nirenska documents her output during her photographic interlude (1967-1980). A few autographed prints of winter scenes by David Hasamatsu comprise the next sub-subseries; the last division of prints is made up of disassembled photograph albums spanning the years 1977 to 1988. The albums contain photographs of Nirenska's travels, family, friends, and pets.
Negatives are arranged in three sections: those of Nirenska alone; those of others; and those by Nirenska. The negatives are all black-and-white and 35 millimeters in size unless noted otherwise; dates are given when known. The first sub-subseries is publicity shots of Nirenska's early solo works. Negatives of others and negatives by Nirenska are similar to the corresponding photoprints sub-subseries. Materials are not cross-referenced.
Slides by Nirenska in the collection are color slides from her photographic interlude period. They are arranged by subject except for a few titled works.
Art work in the collection, consisting of costume designs, drawings, and paintings, complements the choreographic notes and photographic materials. Costume designs by Audrey Cruddas, Doroty Szenfeld, and unidentified designers are from Nirenska's early career in Europe. There are a number of drawings and watercolors of Nirenska and colleagues as well as several miscellaneous drawings and prints.
The audiovisual materials supplement the printed materials related to Nirenska's choreography. Many VHS videotapes and a few 8 millimeter films document dances choreographed during Nirenska's residence in the United States. There are also numerous audio recordings of rehearsals. The video and audio recordings are significant not only for documenting choreographic works, but also for preserving the music of some contemporary women composers. Record albums of music used for accompanying Nirenska's dances are also contained in the collection.
Other materials include: an autographed printed score of Priaulx Rainier's Quartet for strings and a score of the Polish national hymn; poetry for, about, and by Nirenska, and a few miscellaneous poems; subject files of Nirenska's dance school, dance company, and related files containing publicity, programs, clippings, and writings; personal papers such as addresses and cards, bibliographic cards, business papers, and medical documents; four awards including Nirenska's diploma from Mary Wigman's school; realia such as a medal from the 200th anniversary of the Polish Ballet; monographs related to dance, religion, and history; and magazines, articles, and clippings saved by Nirenska mostly pertaining to dance-related topics.
Organization of the Pola Nirenska Collection
The Pola Nirenska Collection is organized in 15 series:
Biographical Materials
Correspondence
Choreographic Notes
Programs
Publicity
Scrapbooks
Photographic Materials
Art Work
Music
Poetry
Subject Files
Personal Papers
Awards
Realia
Books and Articles
http://lccn.loc.gov/2003682047
Container List
- Biographical Materials, 1933-1991 (Box 1)
  The Biographical Materials series is represented by to subseries: Clippings & articles and Interviews. Clippings & articles are dating from 1933 to the end of Nirenska's career. Interviews are printed dating from 1966 and 1986, two are pulled from the scrapbooks.
  Arranged by subseries and chronologically
  - Clippings and articles (Box-folder 1/1-4)
    - 1933-47 (Box-folder 1/1)
    - 1948-50 Feb. (Box-folder 1/2)
    - 1950 Feb. (continued)-82 Mar. 11 (Box-folder 1/3)
    - 1982 Sept.-91 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Interviews (Box-folder 1/5-7)
    - Interview by Olga Nuray Olcay for Cumhuriyet, 1966 Dec. 27. Original in Scrapbook no. 9 (Box-folder 1/5)
    - Excerpts from an interview by Suzan Moss, 1986 Feb. 18. Original in Scrapbook no. 12 (Box-folder 1/6)
    - Interview and commentary by Priaulx Rainier [?], 1986 May 12 (Box-folder 1/7)
- Correspondence, 1934-1992 (Box 1-3)
  The Correspondence series consists of general correspondence, primarily letters to Nirenska from students and colleagues.
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent
  - Allen-Piper, Christie, 1985 (2 items) (Box-folder 2/1)
  - "A" miscellaneous (Box-folder 2/2)
  - Beauvoir, The National Cathedral Elementary School, 1960 (1 item) (Box-folder 2/3)
  - Birch, Nathan see: The Next Ice Age
  - "B" miscellaneous (Box-folder 2/4)
  - Commission on the Arts and Humanities, District of Columbia, 1983-84 (4 items) (Box-folder 2/5)
  - Connecticut College School of Dance, 1964-65 (3 items) (Box-folder 2/6)
  - "C" miscellaneous (Box-folder 2/7)
  - Dance Exchange, 1987, 1991, n.d. (3 items) (Box-folder 2/8)
  - Dobkiewicz, Major Waclaw, 1941 (1 item) (Box-folder 2/9)
  - "D" miscellaneous (Box-folder 2/10)
  - Eiko & Koma, 1987, n.d. (2 items) (Box-folder 2/11)
  - Fasulo, Teo, 1935 (1 item) (Box-folder 2/12)
  - "F" miscellaneous (Box-folder 2/13)
  - Garretson, Cecily, 1965-66, 1988-91 (10 items) (Box-folder 2/14)
  - Gelenian, Seda, n.d. (1 item) (Box-folder 2/15)
  - Graham, Martha, 1966 (2 items) (Box-folder 2/16)
  - "G" miscellaneous (Box-folder 2/17)
  - Hartke, Rev. Gilbert V., 1960-63, n.d. (3 items) (Box-folder 2/18)
  - Henderson, Robert, 1949 (1 item) (Box-folder 2/19)
  - Horne, J. P. (Georgie), 1988, 1991 (3 items) (Box-folder 2/20)
  - Horst, Louis, n.d. (1 item) (Box-folder 2/21)
  - Humphrey, Doris, 1958 (1 item) (Box-folder 2/22)
  - "H" miscellaneous (Box-folder 2/23)
  - "I" miscellaneous (Box-folder 2/24)
  - John F. Kennedy Center for the Performing Arts, 1987 (1 item) (Box-folder 2/25)
  - Jooss, Kurt, 1934 (2 items) (Box-folder 2/26)
  - Juilliard School of Music, 1958 (2 items) (Box-folder 2/27)
  - "J" miscellaneous (Box-folder 2/28)
  - Karski, Jan, 1960, 1966, 1992, n.d. (5 items) (Box-folder 2/29)
  - Kauffman, Edith W., 1965-66, n.d. (8 items) (Box-folder 2/30)
  - Kreutzberg, Harald, n.d. (1 item) (Box-folder 2/31)
  - "K" miscellaneous (Box-folder 2/32)
  - Laban, Juana de, 1951 (1 item) (Box-folder 2/33)
  - Laban, Rudolf, 1949-50 (3 items) (Box-folder 2/34)
  - L'Ecole Libanaise de Ballet, 1967 (2 items) (Box-folder 2/35)
  - Ledesma, J. J. de [Count John Ledesma], 1985 (1 item) (Box-folder 2/36)
  - Legters, Phyllis [?], 1968 (1 item) (Box-folder 2/37)
  - Lerman, Liz, 1991, n.d. (3 items) (Box-folder 2/38)
  - Lerner, Marcia [?], 1962, n.d. (2 items) (Box-folder 2/39)
  - "L" miscellaneous (Box-folder 2/40)
  - Madden, Dorothy, 1960, 1991 (3 items) (Box-folder 2/41)
  - Manning, Susan, 1987 (1 item) (Box-folder 2/42)
  - Maynard, Allegra, 1960, n.d. (2 items) (Box-folder 2/43)
  - Metropolitan Dance Association, 1980 (2 items) (Box-folder 2/44)
  - Michaeli, Katia, 1991 (5 items) (Box-folder 2/45)
  - "M" miscellaneous (Box-folder 2/46)
  - National Section on Dance, 1964 (1 item) (Box-folder 2/47)
  - The Next Ice Age [Nathan Birch], 1991 (10 items) (Box-folder 2/48)
  - "N" miscellaneous (Box-folder 2/49)
  - Opera Society of Washington, 1960 (1 item) (Box-folder 2/50)
  - Osgood Chanock, Beth, 1963 (1 item) (Box-folder 2/51)
  - "O" miscellaneous (Box-folder 2/52)
  - Pearson, Nicole, n.d. (1 item) (Box-folder 2/53)
  - Piedmont Day School, 1959 (1 item) (Box-folder 2/54)
  - Pola Nirenska School of Dance, 1968 (1 item). Notification of retirement (Box-folder 2/55)
  - Polish Embassy, London, 1936 (1 item) (Box-folder 2/56)
  - Poulten, Kay, 1948 (3 items) (Box-folder 2/57)